<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter touching the present state of affairs in England with the independency of its kings : in a letter to a gentleman beyond sea / English'd by J.W.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48240</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27404156</idno>
  <idno type="VID">110112</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240871919</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1755A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">27404156</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110112)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter touching the present state of affairs in England with the independency of its kings : in a letter to a gentleman beyond sea / English'd by J.W.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wells ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110112:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER Touching the present <hi>State of Affairs</hi> IN ENGLAND, WITH THE Independency OF ITS KINGS: In a LETTER to a Gentleman Beyond Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>English'd</hi> by <hi>J. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted for <hi>John Wells</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar, Anno Dom.</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:110112:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110112:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER Touching the Present State of Affairs IN ENGLAND, With the Independency of its KINGS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Letter, and do take no little pleasure in answering it, and in giving you an Account how things pass here since the Death of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of Blessed Memory: You say you cannot imagine that there should be so great quietness as is reported; and that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110112:3"/> you will not be beaten out of your Increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unless I assure you of the Truth of things my self: Do not doubt therefore, Sir, seeing it is most certain, that what we have seen of late happened in this Kingdom, hath not caused any alteration in the Repose and Peace that we do here enjoy, the Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of many have proved false and vain, the same Tranquility continues in all parts, the Storms wherewith we were threatned are gone, and served only to trouble the imagination of those that raised them. Our Grief took beginning, and began to discipate both in one day; God was pleased to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of one King, and to give us another at the same instant; and never did any Prince ascend the Throne with greater ease than the present King. He was Proclaimed to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of all His Subjects, and if the Joy was not excessive, it was the sense of the late loss of the best of Kings, who governed His People more like a Father than a Master, was the cause that hinder'd the manifesting of it: However, a general Submission was given, the Sound passed from the Court to the City, and from the City was spread through the Three Nations.</p>
            <p>The publick Profession the King made sense few days after of a Religion contrary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110112:3"/> unto that of His Subjects; was so far from changing, that it did not in the least shake the Peoples Obedience. But Sir, this need not seem strange unto you, you being of a Religion contrary unto the Principles of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is not your belief that Subjects can be freed from the Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance they owe unto their Soveraign, under a pretence that they are of a contrary Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, you hate these Maxims; You as well as all <hi>Protestants</hi> do believe that the Conscience should be free, that every one should be led by the Dictates of his own Soul; and that the difference of Religion should not serve as a Cloak to trouble the Order and Peace of the World, and violate the most Sacred and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Duties. As a Father cannot deprive his Son of his Birth-right, only for not being of his Belief, without violating the Laws of Nature; neither can Subjects, (without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themselves guilty by the like reason,) deny unto their Soveraigns the Enjoyment of the Throne, which God and Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stows upon them. This is the Doctrine of <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here, Sir, in what manner the <hi>Confession of Faith</hi> of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France</hi> Expresses it self upon this matter. <hi>We believe God requires the World should be governed by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110112:4"/> Laws, to serve as a Curb to restrain the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders which are too rife in it: To this purpose he has Establish'd Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, and all other sorts of Powers whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, whereof He is the Chief Founder, putting the Sword into Magistrates Hands to punish Sins committed against both Tables of Gods Law; Therefore we should not only submit unto their Authority for Conscience sake, but also Honour and Respect them as Gods Vicegerents appointed to execute a Holy and Lawful Authority upon Earth. We believe therefore Obedience is to be given to their Laws, that Custom and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute should be pay'd unto them; And that we should give a free and voluntary Subjection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them,</hi> although they were Infidels.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, is what our <hi>Doctors</hi> have, and do constantly Teach. I could alledge a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand instances of it, but I will mention but in one, which relates unto <hi>England</hi> in the present Circumstances that Kingdom is in, which all the Ministers of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Churches of <hi>France</hi> will sign with their Blood.</p>
            <p>Some time before K. <hi>Charles</hi> the II. was Restor'd to the Throne of his Father, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Enemies he had in his Kingdoms spread abroad Rumours, That He was not of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> but held correspondence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110112:4"/> with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that for that Reason it was not safe to Restore Him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in all likelihood he would by degrees Suppress the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> and if he could, would Establish that of the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This noise having been spread over <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> Monsieur <hi>De Langle,</hi> Senior Minister of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Church near <hi>Roan,</hi> published a Treatise upon this Subject, Entituled, <hi>The Religion of the King of</hi> England. And having refuted this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny by Un-answerable Proofs, he affirms, that if the King of <hi>England</hi> had Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> yet his Subjects ought not in Justice to oppose his Return to his Crown and Establishment in his Kingdoms. <hi>I cannot see</hi> (saith he) <hi>that it is a sufficient Warrant to deprive a man of his Right, because he is not of the same mind we are of in matters of Religion; I most willingly shun these rigid Opinions which Subvert the Foundation of Kingdoms, and make the Christian Religion incompatible with all the Religions in the World; and willingly leave them unto those deluded persons that think the Earth belongs only to the Saints, such as they fancy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be; and that which is enjoy'd by others who are not of the number of these deluded Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110112:5"/> is held Ʋnjustly and by Ʋsurpation; and therefore by consequence, I am very far from thinking that the People of</hi> England <hi>had any good ground for Deposing their Lawful Prince from his Throne under pretext that he was of a Religion contrary to theirs: I know this has not been the practice of the People of God; and under the Legal Dispensation since the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the</hi> Jews, <hi>was transferr'd over into the Hands of Kings, People never Rebell'd against their Princes for their being</hi> Idolators, <hi>unless they had an express Command of God for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far Monsieur <hi>De Langle.</hi> And it is the constant and universal Doctrine which the <hi>Protestants</hi> have taught and published to the World ever since they began to Reform the Church; This is the commendation their very Enemies give them. Cardinal <hi>Du Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> writing against the King of <hi>Great Britain James</hi> the I. acknowledges, <hi>That the Doctrine of Deposing Kings by the</hi> Pope <hi>was received in</hi> France <hi>until the</hi> Reformation, <hi>and that the</hi> Hereticks (so he is pleas'd to call the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants) having brought the Scriptures to Light, vindicated the Right of Kings, which before had been Suppress'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when <hi>Sextus</hi> the V. published his thundring <hi>Bulls</hi> against the King of <hi>Navar</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110112:5"/> and Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> wherein He by Infinite Degrees exalts the Power and Authority of the <hi>Pope</hi> above that of all the Kings of the Earth, so far as to say, <hi>That when they fail of their Duty and Obedience to him, he is able to cast them down from their Thrones by Irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Decrees and Judgments, and bring them under his Power as Ministers of Satan.</hi> Who did ever more vindicate and assert the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of Kings, in respect of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, from all other Powers, except of God only, with greater Evidence, than the <hi>French Protestants</hi> have done. It may be some will reply, their Deeds has not always been suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Words, having more than once preferr'd their Inclinations to Rebellion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that of their Obedience- This Calumny has been often imputed unto Us and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and has been a thousand times Refuted and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>swered.</p>
            <p>I shall only reply in two words, and make two or three brief reflections: The first is the Testimony render'd by the Wisest King that lived in his time, <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. to our Innocence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Subject, in the Book he writ of the Right of Kings.</p>
            <p>He was a Prince Learned and Judicious, he knew perfectly well by what motive So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns and Subjects did Act, and the cause
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110112:6"/> and ground of their Difference. He was no way concern'd in their quarrel, and doth speak only to give a publick Testimony to Truth. This Prince expresses himself after this manner, <hi>I am not</hi> (saith he) <hi>of those that say the</hi> French Protestants <hi>took up Arms against their Kings in the first Troubles, they kept themselves only in a Defensive posture; Before they took up Arms they were Burnt, they were Massacred in all parts; And that the quarrel was not upon Account of Religion, but it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause</hi> Francis <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>being in Minority, the Princes of the Blood were driven from Court; the Father of the King that now Reigns, and the Prince of</hi> Conde <hi>fled to them, not knowing where else to go; And for this very reason the King ought to Consider them. It doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that ever they began a War: Is it not evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> III. <hi>having taken up Arms to destroy them, nevertheless they assisted him; and seeing him in danger delivered him, and sav'd his Life at</hi> Tours, <hi>and never forsook him and his Successor; notwithstanding the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of the greatest part of his Subjects, which had been caused and fomented by the</hi> Pope <hi>and the Clergy. Is it not plain that they assisted him in all his Engagements, and happily Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to Establish his Tottering Crown on his Head; And even those that persecuted</hi> Henry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110112:6"/>
               <hi>the</hi> IV. <hi>reaped the benefit of Services done him by</hi> Protestants, <hi>and yet they are hated, not for disputing of Religion, but because they hinder'd the Kings Crown to depend on the</hi> Pope; <hi>And because, if their Councel had been followed, there should no</hi> French-men <hi>have been excused from obeying their Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in this manner this Religious and Learned Prince doth vindicate our Ancestors; But let us suppose our Fathers should have fallen in to this Crime: should a Religion be Censur'd by the Actions of those that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess it? If so, there is no Religion whereunto the greatest Disorders may not be imputed. We all equally condemn Adultery, Murder, Lying, Robbery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And because there are some amongst us that fall into these sins, does it follow that our Religion doth Tolerate these Crimes; are they not chiefly to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the disorder and corruption of the Hearts of Men; it is the same in this rencounter. Religion enjoyns <hi>Protestants</hi> to give Obedience to Princes, warns them that nothing can dispense them from their Duty; that rather then fail in it, 'twere better suffer the most Cruel Torments; Yet it falls out, that Subjects constrain'd by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Persecution, have endeavour'd to save their Lives by defending themselves; And this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110112:7"/> which though Natural, yet cannot be Innocent, shall it be imputed to a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which, to establish the Kingdom of God, only teacheth to suffer Patiently, and even Martyrdom?</p>
            <p>Moreover, Sir, when these ways which somewhat resembled violence were used, it was at the beginning of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> when the Heart and Mind of <hi>Protestants</hi> had as yet some smack of these Maxims, that all means should be undertaken to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve Religion; But now that the World is better inform'd, and that in the whole <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Body, there remains not the least drop of this corrupt Blood, with which the Veins of the <hi>Romish Clergy</hi> did over-flow: It is not to be admired if they willingly submit to the Power of their Soveraign, although he be of a contrary Religion. It is what is at this time practis'd by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for all the Worlds Imitation, which may serve as an evident Justification from all the Calumnies which the Enemies of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion</hi> undeservedly spew out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them in the view of all the World.</p>
            <p>In effect, the <hi>Clergy</hi> is seen to Act with a Spirit of Wisdom and Moderation, full of Zeal for their Soveraign, infusing Notions of Duty and Obedience into the People whose
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110112:7"/> Salvation is committed to their Charge, both by their Doctrine and Example; And herein, Sir, they do but their Duty; Jesus Christ himself having taught us this Obedience by his Words and Deeds. He was the King of Kings, nevertheless he was pleas'd to submit unto their Power; he contented not himself to command his Disciples to render unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> the things that were <hi>Caesars;</hi> he requir'd nothing of others, but what he did himself. he was pleas'd herein to be their Example: The <hi>Jews</hi> being ravish'd with his Doctrine and Miracles, run from all parts to make him a King, but he withdrew into the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sart, to shew to the World that he was not come to Command, and Subvert the Establish'd Order, but to teach Obedience and Humility to his followers; this is the Doctrine was taught by the Apostles after the Example of their Master, commanding all Christians without exception, <hi>To be Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient unto Higher Powers;</hi> It is also what was Religiously practis'd by Christians in the first Ages of the Church.</p>
            <p>It is in this Noble Path the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> treads at this time; and I cannot tell but its Obedience shines brighter than that which appear'd after the Death of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles. Those that embrac'd the Gospel at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110112:8"/> that time were but very few in comparison of the rest, the greater numbers were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them, in regard Necessity as well as Conscience made them to submit and suffer Death Patiently: They could do no otherwise, it being in vain to resist, and a means only to double their Torments, and make their condition more Miserable: This circumstance is not to be seen in the submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they are all a <hi>Protestant</hi> People, who voluntarily Obey and Submit to the Laws of a Prince who is of another contrary perswasion.</p>
            <p>Pardon me, Sir, for what I shall say of the <hi>Primitive Christians,</hi> it is not altogether without ground. When they began to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and make some Figure in the World, they kept not the same moderation as at first. Tho great men, which Antiquity renders so venerable to us, were seen to forget the Respect they ow'd to Soveraigns; and by angry and indiscreet Invectives blasted the Reputation and Honour was due to their Quality. Nothing of this kind can be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Prelates and Ministers of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They Preach their Doctrine, they Refute that of <hi>Rome,</hi> they discharge their Duty without making any Indiscreet or hurtful Reflections, or without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110112:8"/> offending a Crown'd Head; in so doing, they more and more fill the Hearts of their Auditors with a Spirit of Love and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience for their Soveraign, thereby equally maintaining the Priviledges both of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, if the meekness of our Bishops and their humble and submissive manner of acting, doth, in this behalf give Lessons to to <hi>Ambross</hi>'s and <hi>Chrisostom</hi>'s, doth it not also highly condemn the Opinions and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of <hi>Rome.</hi> Should the King of <hi>Spain</hi> come to perceive that the Religion profess'd in his Kingdom is full of gross Superstition, and that he had courage enough to set about ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God in a purer manner in some part of his Palace? Think you that <hi>Spain</hi> would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it? Should one see all the Bodies of the Kingdom come gravely and renew the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of their Zeal and Fidelity to their Soveraign; would the <hi>Inquisition,</hi> without Sighing, behold this change with a good Eye? Would it spare its Soveraign, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its opinion would be guilty of <hi>Heresie;</hi> who upon bare Suspition exercis'd its Infernal Cruelty upon <hi>Don Carlos</hi> the next Heir of the Crown: No Sir, without any regard of Dignity all Torments must be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, Life as well as the Crown must be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110112:9"/> forfeited; and to punish such a Defection more dangerous in a Prince than a private person, I cannot tell but some <hi>Daemon</hi> might inspire those Barbarous Ministers with some new kind of Tortures to terrify Kings, and shew them that the Chains which fasten them to <hi>Rome</hi> can never be broken.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Maimbourg</hi> would be extreamly pleas'd with Subjects, who on such an occasion would Rebel against their Prince; him who in an <hi>Iconoclastick.</hi> History, <hi>Highly praises the people of</hi> Constantinople <hi>for abusing their Emperour and Master with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Indignities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hist. des I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noclast. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> He would be far from blaming the Cities that should throw off their Princes Soveraignty, seeing that in the same History he approves, <hi>That</hi> Rome <hi>and the other Cities in</hi> Italy <hi>refus'd to give Obedience to the Emperour too, and were for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying his Effigies, because he was an</hi> Icono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clastick.</p>
            <p>That the Women should have Courage enough to engage in the Quarrel, and take up Arms in the Defence of Religion, should be esteemed incomparable <hi>Heroins</hi> by him, as those of <hi>Constantinople</hi> were, whom he terms Valiant Women, who having knock'd down an Enemy of Image Worship, <hi>Transported</hi> (saith he) <hi>by the Inconceivable heat of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110112:9"/> Zeal, entring into the Church in great and Tumultuous numbers, armed with Stones and Clubs, they discharged them in whole Volleys upon the Patriarchs Head, who was an</hi> Iconoclastick, <hi>calling him Mercenary, Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and a Devouring Woolf in Sheeps-cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, loading him with a</hi> 1000 <hi>other Injuries as well as Blows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, Sir, put the Case the <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi> could not prevail, and that a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Faithful Subjects should assist the King, how would this Author extol the Wisdom and Piety of the <hi>Pope,</hi> who would make sure of the Forces of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great to Dis-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne him, as he does the Zeal of <hi>Gregory</hi> the II. who joyned with <hi>Charles Martel</hi> to deprive <hi>Leo</hi> of his <hi>Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us yet go further, should <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great himself, who is so much Fear'd and Lov'd of his Subjects; add unto the other care he takes of making his Empire Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, cause himself to be a little inform'd of the Religion which he takes so much pains to banish out of His Kingdom; should Heaven open his Eyes as it did <hi>Charles</hi> V. to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Purity of it, and after the Example of that Great Prince, to Repent of the Evils that causes so many to suffer, and to his last gasp make profession of it in some <hi>Desart.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110112:10"/> But carrying true Christian Generosity yet further, should he act with that Air of greatness and Bravery as he doth in all other things, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To make open profession of the Truth before all the World? Think you that it would be suffer'd, though he should Solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promise unto his Subjects that he would change nothing in Church nor State; that he would protect the <hi>Romish Catholicks,</hi> that he would suffer none of the <hi>Huguonot</hi> Churches to be re-built, that he only desired to hear a Sermon without noise or stir in some private Appartment in the <hi>Louvre.</hi> Do you think the Clergy would consent unto it? That the Bishops so naturally inclin'd to complying with the Times, and in following the Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Motions of their own Heart, would have so much complaisance? No Sir, all the World wou'd presently be up in an Alarm, the League would revive worse than ever; the Heads of Factions would soon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; the Holy League would arise and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require as it did heretofore, the Magistrates to joyn with the People to destroy the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Church and State, and to declare that the <hi>French</hi> were discharg'd from their Oaths of Fidelity to their Prince, and that his Name should no more be inserted in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Acts. The Pulpits would no longer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110112:10"/> Eccho the praises due unto the Glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great; those impudent Preachers that spawn'd the League would soon appear again to spread abroad Satyrs, Invectives, Seditious Libels, and to spew out the blackest Injuries, the least of which should be Tyrant and Apostate.</p>
            <p>And the people inspired with the same Spirit, with the greatest brutality of rage would soon vent their fury upon his Arms, his Statues, Effigies and Pictures, which they would tear, break to pieces, tread under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, drag through Kennels, burn and fling into the River, with a thousand Execrations. This is the usage <hi>France</hi> heretofore gave its Sovereign, although he was a Zealous <hi>Papist,</hi> only for making an Alliance with <hi>Protestants,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Maimbourg</hi> relates in his History of the League: I have recited the very words. The which usage a <hi>Protestant</hi> King would also at this time be sure to find, and 'tis not much to be wonder'd at; for the <hi>Pope</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating those Princes that are not of his Belief, doth free their Subjects from the Fidelity they owe unto him, exposing their Persons and Kingdoms unto those can first seize them, promising Plenary Indulgence of all Sins, and even Heaven it self unto those that shall deprive him of Life, as appears by the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110112:11"/>
               <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> the III. which declares <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. King of <hi>England</hi> to be fallen from his Kingdom and Estates, unworthy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Burial, and adjudg'd to Eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the virtue of his Power, if he dies before he be Absolved; and unless he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal the Laws he had Enacted against the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi> the XIV. wherein this <hi>Pope</hi> having taken much pains to shew his great Power, and how God had Establish'd the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> Prince over all Nations and Kingdoms, to destroy, to pluck up, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate, consume, plant and build, he adds, <hi>That by Virtue of this Power, he did Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize, Degrade and Depose,</hi> Elizabeth <hi>Queen of</hi> England, <hi>Absolve her Subjects from their Oath of Fidelity, and absolutely forbids them not to give her any further Obedience:</hi> Who doth not see that a Prince that Reigns over a People that enter into these engagements and Opinions of <hi>Rome,</hi> cannot live in any safety of his Life, and is necessitated to live always in continual Fears and Dangers.</p>
            <p>The Example of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly serve to justify what I affirm; the Crown of <hi>France</hi> was his undoubted Right after the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the III. his Pretentions unto it were undenyable. Nevertheless, was not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110112:11"/> he constrained to abandon his Religion to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the quiet possession of it. Some of his Intimate Friends, whom this Prince much relyed upon, and who were sensible of his Valour, advis'd him to persevere; and that notwithstanding all oppositions God would set him on his Throne. But there were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that whisper'd him, that if he persisted in his Religion, he must expect to take Arms again, and wade through a longer and greater War then was past, that he must expect to give Battles and prepare for Sieges, which so dis-heartned him, that love of rest and the Pleasures of a Crown prevail'd with him to agree to change, more than the other good Instructions, to persevere in the Truth.</p>
            <p>It's most certain, Sir, this Prince his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance in his Religion would have expos'd him unto unavoidable dangers; for after this comantory Libel of <hi>Gregory</hi> the XIII. dated the 1st. of <hi>May,</hi> Directed first to all the <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> whom he Suspends and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates, if in 15 days they do not retire from Obeying and following <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navar:</hi> And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; declaring that in other 15 days, if they did not wholly forsake him, they should be depriv'd of their Estates and Benefices: After
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110112:12"/> this Comantory, he writes of the same date unto the Nobility, the Magistrates and the three Estates of <hi>France,</hi> wherein he Invites them to do the like; threatning, if they did not, to change his Fatherly Clemency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Severity of an Angry Judge: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring moreover, <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> to be Excommunicate, fallen from his Kingdoms and Estates for being a <hi>Heretick</hi> and Relaps. After all this, what safety could this Prince hope to find in his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>I know very well that these two <hi>Bulls</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought into <hi>France,</hi> the Parliament then sitting at <hi>Chaalons,</hi> at a motion made by the Kings Attourney General, they were declared Injurious, Difamatory, Scandalous, tending to Sedition, and to the ruine of the Kingdom, of the House and Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and to the introducing of Strangers. Defence was made to all persons of what condition or quality soever, to publish or or use the said <hi>Bulls</hi> Directly or Indirectly. Neither am I ignorant, how the Court sitting at <hi>Towers,</hi> proceeded yet further, for the 5th. of <hi>August</hi> in the same year, it caused the <hi>Popes</hi> Bull to be publickly Burnt by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hangman, forbiding any to obey it, or keep Copies of it, declar'd <hi>Gregory</hi> an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110112:12"/> of the Peace and union of the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apostolick Roman Church,</hi> of the King and his Kingdom, an Adherent unto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy of <hi>Spain,</hi> a Favourer of Rebels, guilty of the most Cruel, Inhumane and Detestable Murder committed in the Person of <hi>Henry</hi> the III. of Glorious Memory, most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and Catholick. Order'd that <hi>Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Adrianus</hi> the said <hi>Gregory</hi>'s <hi>Nuncio,</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the said <hi>Bulls,</hi> should be seiz'd and sent Prisoner to the <hi>Palace-Prison,</hi> that his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess and Sentence might be dispatch'd in due form; Enjoyning all Governours to Aid and Assist in Executing this Sentence; and to all Archbishops and Bishops to signify It unto the Clergy of their Respective Diocesses.</p>
            <p>I confess this proceeding is Generous, Bold, and Worthy so August an Assembly, but would all <hi>France</hi> have follow'd these Dictates, and would it have been of this Humour; if <hi>Henry</hi> the Great had persever'd in his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; would not the Directors of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Confessors, Preachers and Doctors have inspir'd the People in their private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, Confessions and Sermons, other contrary Notions; as they did a little before in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the III. as is declar'd by the said Mr. <hi>Maimbourg</hi> in his History of of the League. The <hi>Sorbon</hi> it self, would it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110112:13"/> not have Authoriz'd them; she who being Interrogated upon these two great Cases of Conscience: First, if the <hi>French</hi> were effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally free'd from their Oaths of Fidelity and Obedience? And in the second place, if they might take up Arms and Unite, Raise Money and Act for the Defence of the <hi>Catholick Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick Roman Religion</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> to oppose the detestable Designs and Endeavours of the King and all his Adherents. They concluded on these two points with one accord <hi>Nemine Contradicente</hi> in the Affirmative, and that their Resolution should be sent to the <hi>Pope,</hi> that he might approve and confirm it by his Authority: and that he would be so kind to assist the <hi>Gallican Church</hi> that Suffer'd very much and was sore oppress'd.</p>
            <p>Believe me, Sir, all the light and force of this Decree would not have remov'd the Scruples and dissipated the fears that the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Vatican</hi> had rais'd in the minds of men: On the contrary, all the Orders of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> would with one accord have esteem'd it a point of Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to have oppos'd it, and so the K's Life had not been in safety had he 100000 men in Arms for his Defence, all his care would have been in vain, there would soon have been seen many furies animated with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110112:13"/> Zeal that would have past through his Guards to Stab him, and stop the course of his Life, together with his Conquests and his Glory; imagining for so doing to die hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and increase the Catalogue of Saints.</p>
            <p>A Prince of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Reigning over <hi>Protestant</hi> Subjects, stands not in any such danger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Principles of their Religion is quite different, so that he may safely Imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in making his Reign Glorious: It is what the King has taken notice of in his <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and which makes him protect a Church, whose Fidelity he can in no way mistrust, by the Experience he has had of its constant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to the Interests of the Crown in the time of the late Usurper. The King is pleas'd, Sir, to renew the assurance of His Royal Favour unto His Subjects, and especially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arch-Bishops and Bishops, whom he continues to Honour by admitting them into his weightiest Affairs and Councils, mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acting in Business without any Suspition on either part; the King fully Confiding and Relying upon the Clergy, and the Clergy full of Obedience and Zeal for their Soveraign.</p>
            <p>This, Sir, is the State this Kingdom is in at present; quite contrary as you see, from what 'tis represented unto you: Believe not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110112:14"/> therefore all that is Reported, give no Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit unto Flying News that's spread abroad, the most part is only Forgeries, given out on purpose to discourage <hi>Protestants,</hi> and to breed Divisions in <hi>England:</hi> The King will Defend them he has taken into his Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is his Promise, and he has reiterated it again at His Coronation in the most Solemn and August manner in the World, and He will Infallibly perform it: He ever made it a point of Honour to keep His Word in matters of less Importance; and he will not fail in this, and will preserve the Repute now He sits on the Throne, which He so punctually observ'd before he ascended thither. He will never be perswaded by any Whispering <hi>Romish</hi> Emissaries, that his Faith and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise ought not to be kept with <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Infidels;</hi> His Heart is Season'd with Juster and better Principles; and He is very sensible nothing has more Dishonour'd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion than these Pernicious Maxims and Breaches of Promise, which has drawn upon it many great Evils and Heavy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches from its Enemies.</p>
            <p>Moreover, every body knows there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more contributes to make a Kingdom flourish and Happy, than a right understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt the Soveraign and His Subjects;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110112:14"/> the Kings own Interest will oblige Him to preserve things in the State they are in. He is sensible that His Peoples Religion being Secur'd unto them, there is not one of His Subjects but will readily Sacrifice his Life and Fortune for the Defence of His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and also to enlarge the Bounds of it. What danger is there, that a Prince whose whole Life has been Eminent by many Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Actions, now that he is mounted on the Throne, and in a condition of shewing unto the World the value of so War-like a People as his, being conducted by the Bravest Prince in the World: What danger is there I say, that He will do or Attempt any thing that should be contrary to his Inclination and Honour. He is very sensible how prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial this Zeal for the <hi>Romish Religion</hi> has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> He knows it has lately reduc'd the Emperour to those miserable Straits, from which he is not yet Recover'd; and doubtless He perceives as well as all the World, that it is the same Blind Zeal that is preparing the way to the Miseries that threaten <hi>France,</hi> and which is almost inevitable to all Kingdoms when they have attain'd the highest degree of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110112:15"/>
            <p>Yes, Sir, and I don't pretend to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in saying it, seeing it is obvious to every body; what all the World joyn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether could not effect, <hi>France</hi> is doing of it self; it is its Fate to sink under its own great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and to procure and work its own Ruine and Destruction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Protestants</hi> for above an Age ago were not so Inconsiderable in this Kingdom, as to be cut off without doing it a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice: It is the smallest, but the most Loyal Party of the State; and has been always ready to oppose the Parties that have been contrary to the Crown. It is They that have caused Traffique and the Arts to flourish, and have more than once produced Generals, Great Commanders, and Valiant Troops that have preserv'd <hi>France</hi> when it was at the brink of Ruin: Nevertheless these <hi>Protestants</hi> are Assaulted, they are Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all parts in the Cruellest manner that can be. Were they more despicable than they be, were they the least and vilest part of the State; yet common sense would require that they should be preserv'd, least this Empire should like the King of <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Image, see the destruction of his more Noble parts, his head and Arms of Gold and Silver, by his Feet of Iron and Clay. As in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110112:15"/> Body, the parts the least Honourable, ought sometimes to have the greatest Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; so also in a Political State, all the Members whereof it is Compos'd, ought to be Cherish'd and preserv'd. There is no question then to be made Sir, but the King will according to his Promise, be inclin'd to protect His Subjects, and will make good use of his Neighbours Miscarriages: He Loves His People, He will Imploy His Forces to preserve them, He Loves His Glory, and will do nothing that shall diminish it; the Bonds of Nature is Dear unto Him, He hears its voice, and will maintain the Religion that His Glorious Father Sealed with His own Blood.</p>
            <p>I cannot pass further, and end my Letter, without intimating unto you the wonders of the Mercy and Providence of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the last two Kings. All the World knows the Tragical end of the Glorious Prince their Father. A company of Rebels by an Audatious Attempt pronounc'd or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hell by their mouth pronounc'd a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Sentence, which caused the Glorious Head that Govern'd three Kingdoms to be cut off by Violent Hands; And Heaven to Reward his Patience and Virtues, not only gave him an Eternal Kingdom of Glory, but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110112:16"/> also is pleas'd to suffer, that two Branches proceeding from him, should successively Ascend his Throne; that living and Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, he should in some sort be Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penc'd for the loss of those days which Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Tyrany depriv'd Him of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>